Guide to the Gerald H. Beard Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Gerald H. Beard Papers
1866-1938
RG 65
Yale University Divinity School Library
12
(28 boxes)
Gerald Hamilton Beard was born in Hammersmith, England in 1862. He received the B.A., B.D. and Ph.D. degrees from Yale. He was a Congregational clergyman with pastorates in Norwalk and Bridgeport, Connecticut and Burlington, Vermont during the years 1892-1921. He was an Alumni Lecturer at Yale Divinity School in 1910. He died in 1921.; total linear footage Of particular interest in the collection is the fairly complete file of sermons and addresses delivered during the period 1888-1921. These sermons, in conjunction with Beard's extensive subject file, provide a valuable record of the style and content of preaching of a successful Congregational minister during a time of liberal resurgence in American Protestantism. The sermons address the urban problems of the Gilded Age. With the onset of the First World War, Beard participated in the prevailing surge of patriotism bolstered by theology.'
Beard, Gerald Hamilton, 1862-1921
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1862 Born in Hammersmith, England
1877-1884 In stationery business with his brother
1887 B.A., Yale; was elected to Phi Beta Kappa and was member of Pundit Club
1890 B.D., Yale; received John Addison Porter prize and Dwight fellowship
1892 Ph.D., Yale
1892 Married to Mary Keyes of Minneapolis, who became the mother of his four daughters
1892 Ordained; took up first pastorale at First Congregational Church, Norwalk, Connecticut
1900-1904 Pastor of College Street Congregational Church, Burlington, Vermont
1904-1921 Pastor of Park Street Congregational Church, Bridgeport, Connecticut
1910 Alumni lecturer, Yale Divinity School
1921 Retired to New Hampshire with family, due to ill health. Died October 10.
Scope and Contents
Of most interest in the collection is the fairly complete file of sermons and addresses delivered during the period 1888 to 1921. These sermons, in conjunction with Beard's extensive subject file, provide a valuable record of the style and content of preaching of a successful Congregational minister during a time of liberal resurgence in American Protestantism. Beard came to the ministry from a brilliant undergraduate and graduate career at Yale. He was well equipped to grapple with the intellectual challenges facing liberal theologians of his times, such as historical criticism of the Bible, evolution, and the relationship between science and religion. During his seventeen years of ministry in Bridgeport, Connecticut)Beard was brought face to face with the urban problems of the Gilded Age. His sermons express concern with the issues of temperance, vice, housing and education. With the onset of the First World War, Beard participated in the prevailing surge of patriotism bolstered by theology. Regardless of the topic he addressed, Beard's views were informed by the spirit of confidence and hope typical of a pre-War civilization in which the ideals and patterns of American life were nearly equated with those of American Protestantism.
The first six folders in Series I, Correspondence, contain letters to and from family members. The small amount of General Correspondence which follows reflects Beard's interests in church affairs, reform, and relief. Several letters relate to the transfer of church membership. Beard wrote an article about the conditions of church membership which was responded to by various individuals, including Timothy Dwight and George B. Stevens of Yale. Other letters relate to the Knights of King Arthur boys club format which Beard was considering for his church. There are also letters of opinion written by Beard to President Woodrow Wilson, and a Senator, and letters stemming from Beard's service as chairman of the local branch of the American Committee for Armenian and Syrian Relief.
There are nearly l,000 sermons and addresses in Series II. They vary in format from complete typescripts, to fragmentary holograph notes to published newspaper accounts. In a few cases only the title page of a sermon exists, with an indication that the body of the sermon was destroyed. The majority of the sermons are in one numerical sequence dating from 1892 to 1921. This sequence is preceded by seven early sermons which are designated by letter. Following the numerical sequence are several unnumbered sermons, sermon fragments,and one folder of undated children's sermons.
The sermons are not listed individually by title. The following list of titles will serve to suggest the range of topics covered:
"Are Both God and the Earthquake Possible?"
"Real Results of Prayer"
"Personal Character and Public Office"
"The Fight Against Tuberculosis"
"Theodore Roosevelt -- President"
"The Influence of the Well Housed Home"
"Sunday Laws: Their Use and Abuse"
"Our Duty as American Citizens"
"Tennyson's Religious Influence"
"Joining the Color for Christ"
"The Christian Duty of Fighting"
"The Vaudeville Stage in Bridgeport"
"The Great Armenian Tragedy"
"Darwin, Evolution and Christianilv"
"A Working Creed About Miracles"
"The Strength of the Purified Life"
"A Christian Civilization"
"The Christian Gentleman"
"Christian Missions and International Peace"
"Mrs. Eddy and Christian Science"
"Total Abstinence in the Light of the Law of Love"
"Christianity and the Licensed Liquor Saloon"
"Bridgeport and the Kindergarten Education"
"The Self-Complacencies of Orthodoxy"
"The Christianization of America"
"The Biblical Documents -- Are They Trustworthy?"
"Is the Bible Inspired? Is it Authoritative? Is it Useful?"
The writings of Series III are largely undated. The major works are "The History of the Catholic English and of the American Revised Version of the Bible", which won second prize in the Gould Prize Essay contest in 1905, and a long unpublished treatise entitled "The Religion of a Man." Topics which Beard touched on in sermons are developed more extensively in essays included in this Series, such as "The Christian Redemption in the Light of Evolutionary Philosophy" and "Woodrow Wilson, Robert Lansing, and Some Ideals Worth Fighting For."
The Notebooks of Series IV primarily date from Beard's graduate student days at Yale. They are of interest for their record of the content of courses taught at Yale in the early lS90's 1n the subject areas of philosophy, theology and Bible.
Throughout his career, Beard maintained the practice of collecting newspaper and magazine articles, poems, programs, and other ephemera for use in writing sermons. Series V, the subject file which he created, is arranged alphabetically by topic. Materials were stored in manilla envelopes, with topics listed, usually not in exact alphabetical order.
The following topics from the "H" envelopes will serve to suggest the variety of materials collected by Beard:
Honesty
Hell
Home
Health
Hopelessness
Heroism
Home and School
Heredity
Hospitality
Heaven
Holmes, 0. W.
Hewing
Home Education
Healing
Holy Ghost
Hadley, Pres.
House of Lords
Harrison, Pres
Howe, Julia Ward
Halloween
Horticulture
Harper, W. R.
Hymns
Haynes
Hypocrisy
Hay, John
Hyde, George
Happiness
Hypnotism
Hall family
Higher Criticism
Hammurabi
Hindu books
Habit
Hill, E. J.
Hartford Seminary
High School
Hawley
History
Havergal
Humor
Hungarian work
Human touch
Hughes
Hudson-Fulton Celeb.
Huxley
Heresy
Series VI, Personal Items and Memorabilia, includes the invitation to Beard's wedding in 1892, a few notes recording events on the days preceding Beard's death, "Our Church Record for 1900" - annual report of the Pastor of College Street Congregational Church, Burlington, VT, 1901 "The Story of a Church" - history of Park Street Congregational Church by J. S. Wooster, and a notebook of Esther Sophia Deers given to Louise Beard.
Series VII consists of an addendum added in August 2001, which contains correspondence, sermons, writings, and personal items and memorabilia.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1875-1921
II. Sermons and Addresses, 1888-1921
III. Writings, 1885-1917, n.d.
IV. Notebooks, 1891-1892, n.d.
V. Subject File
VI. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1892-1938
VII. Addendum: 2010
Housing; Sermons, American; Social history; Temperance; Urban policy; Bridgeport (Conn.) -- Church history -- Sources; Sermons; Clergy; Beard, Gerald Hamilton, 1862-1921; Park Street Congregational Church (Bridgeport, Conn.)
- Correspondence, 1875-1921; Series I
  - Family Correspondence
    - To GHB from his mother, 1884-1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - From GHB and MKB to his mother, 1888-1902 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - To GHB from wife, 1890-1892, 1907, n.d (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - From GHB to wife, 1900-1901, 1920, n.d (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - To GHB and MKB from daughters, 1921, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - To GHB from siblings; From GHB to sister-in-law, 1875-1908 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence
    - A-D (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - G-M (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - P-W; Christian names (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Sermons, 1888-1921; Series II
  - #A, B, 1888 Jun (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - #D, G, 1888 Jul (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - #J, K, 1888 Aug, Sep (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - #L, 1888 Mar (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - #2, 7, 8, 1892 Oct-Nov (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - #10, 12, 13, 1892 Dec - 1893 Apr (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - #16-120 (37 sermons), 1893 Jan - 1894 Jul (Box 2, Folder 16-28)
  - #121 - 196 (35 sermons), 1894 Sep - l896 Jan (Box 3, Folder 29-40)
  - #198-248 (37 sermons), 1896 Jan- 1897 May (Box 4, Folder 41-51)
  - #249-312 (59 sermons), 1897 May - 1898 Dec (Box 5, Folder 52-63)
  - #313-400 (81 sermons), 1898 Dec - 1900 Feb (Box 6, Folder 63-79)
  - #401-551 (90 sermons), 1900 Mar - 1904 Apr (Box 7, Folder 80-97)
  - #600-683 (85 sermons), 1906 Oct - 1908 Nov (Box 8, Folder 98-114)
  - #684-768 (85 sermons), 1908 Dec - 1910 Jul (Box 9, Folder 115-131)
  - #769-841 (75 sermons), 1910 Sep - 1911 Dec (Box 10, Folder 132-146)
  - #842-914 (74 sermons), 1912 Jan - 1913 May (Box 11, Folder 147-161)
  - #915-1004 (91 sermons), 1913 May - 1914 Dec (Box 12, Folder 162-179)
  - #1004-1095 (91 sermons), 1915 Jan - 1916 Oct (Box 13, Folder 180-197)
  - #1096-1178 (85 sermons), 1916 Oct - 1918 Apr (Box 14, Folder 198-214)
  - #1179-1339 (45 sermons), 1918 Apr - 1921 Jun (Box 15, Folder 215-222)
  - Unnumbered sermons and sermon fragments, 1893-1897 (Box 15, Folder 223)
  - Unnumbered sermons and sermon fragments, 1906,1918, 1919,n.d. (Box 15, Folder 224)
  - Unnumbered sermons and sermon fragments (Box 15, Folder 225)
  - Children's sermons, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 226)
- Writings, 1885-1917, n.d.; Series III
  - "The Religion of Chaucer", 1885 (Box 16, Folder 227)
  - "Statement of Personal Experience and Theological Belief", 1892 (Box 16)
  - "Conditions of Church Membership", 1899 (Box 16)
  - The History of the Catholic English and of the American Revised Version of the Bible -- Gould Prize Essay (published), 1905 (Box 16, Folder 228)
  - Notes for Gould Prize Essay, 1905 (Box 16, Folder 229-233)
  - "A Gladsome Responsibility", 1917 (Box 16, Folder 234)
  - "Evangelism", n.d. (Box 16, Folder 235)
  - "Humans and Simians" (Box 16)
  - "Tennyson's Analytical Power" "Woodrow Wilson, Robert Lansing, and (Box 16)
  - Some Ideals Worth Fighting For", n.d. (Box 16)
  - "The Religion of a Man" pp. 1 - 104, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 236)
  - "The Religion of a Man" pp. 105-221, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 237)
  - "The Religion of a Man" (with annotation) pp. 2-24, 36-116, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 238)
  - "The Religion of a Man" (with annotation) pp. 117-137, 153-221, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 239)
  - Notes for "The Doctrine of the Grace of God", n.d. (Box 17, Folder 240)
  - "The Doctrine of the Incarnation in the Light of the Modern Philosophical Conception of God and the Human Soul" (Box 17, Folder 241)
  - "The Religious Value of a Christian Philosophy of the Immanence of God", n.d. (Box 17, Folder 242)
  - "The Christian Redemption in the Light of Evolutionary Philosophy", n.d. (Box 17, Folder 243)
  - Untitled manuscript pp. 2-61, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 244)
  - Manuscript fragment, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 245)
  - Manuscript fragment, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 246)
- Notebooks, 1891-1892, n.d.; Series IV
  - Hegel, 1892 (Box 17, Folder 247)
  - Bible: I Corinthians exegesis, 1891 (Box 17, Folder 248)
  - New Testament Introduction, 1892 (Box 18, Folder 249)
  - Doctrinal Theology, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 250)
  - Bible: O.T. (English), N.T. (exegesis), n.d. (Box 18, Folder 251)
  - The History of Doctrine, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 252)
  - Biblical Theology, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 253)
  - Miscellaneous -- 2 volumes, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 254)
  - Hebrew Exercises and Pentateuch Criticism (Box 19, Folder 255)
  - Philosophy of the Unconscious Subject, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 256)
  - Messianic Prophecy, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 257)
  - Miscellaneous subjects, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 258)
  - Quotations from readings, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 259)
- Subject File, Series V
  - B - C (Box 19, Folder 260)
  - C (Box 19, Folder 261)
  - D (Box 19, Folder 262)
  - D (Box 20, Folder 263)
  - E (Box 20, Folder 264-265)
  - F (Box 20, Folder 266-267)
  - G (Box 20, Folder 268-269)
  - H (Box 20, Folder 270)
  - H (Box 21, Folder 271)
  - I (Box 21, Folder 272-273)
  - J (Box 21, Folder 274)
  - K (Box 21, Folder 275)
  - M (Box 21, Folder 276-278)
  - N (Box 22, Folder 279-280)
  - 0 (Box 22, Folder 281)
  - P (Box 22, Folder 282-285)
  - R (Box 22, Folder 286)
  - R (Box 23, Folder 287-288)
  - S (Box 23, Folder 289-293)
  - T (Box 23, Folder 294)
  - T (Box 24, Folder 295-296)
  - U (Box 24, Folder 297)
  - V (Box 24, Folder 298)
  - W (Box 24, Folder 299)
  - W - y (Box 24, Folder 300)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 24, Folder 301)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1892-1938; Series VI
  - Wedding invitation, 1892 (Box 24, Folder 302)
  - Items related to GHB's last days, 1921 (Box 24, Folder 303)
  - Annual report of Pastor of College Street Congregational Church, Burlington, CT, 1901 (Box 24, Folder 304)
  - "The Story of Church" - history of Park Street Congregational Church, Bridgeport, CT by John S. Wooster, 1938 (Box 24, Folder 305)
  - Notebook of Esther Sophia Deers given to Louise Beard, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 306)
- Addendum:2001, 1866-1926, n.d.; Series VII
  - Family Correspondence
    - From G.H. Beard to Mother, 1880s-1907 (Box 25, Folder 307)
    - From G.H.B to wife, 1891 Mar-Dec (Box 25, Folder 308)
    - From G.B.H to wife, 1891 Dec 12-1892 (Box 25, Folder 309)
    - To G.B.H from wife, 1890-1892 (Box 25, Folder 310)
    - From G.B.H to Siblings, 1866-1926 (Box 25, Folder 311)
    - To G.B.H from Siblings, 1879-1894 (Box 25, Folder 312)
  - General Correspondence
    - A - W (Box 25, Folder 313)
    - Notebook of Letters 1 (Box 25, Folder 314)
    - Notebook of Letters 2 (Box 25, Folder 315)
    - Notebook of Letters 3 (Box 25, Folder 316)
  - Sermons and Addresses
    - # A, B (Box 26, Folder 317)
    - # C (a) (Box 26, Folder 318)
    - # C (b) (Box 26, Folder 319)
    - # D, F, G (Box 26, Folder 320)
    - # I, L (Box 26, Folder 321)
    - # M, O, P (Box 26, Folder 322)
    - # R (Box 26, Folder 323)
    - # S, T (Box 26, Folder 324)
    - # V, W (Box 26, Folder 325)
    - Christmas and New Year Greetings (Box 26, Folder 326)
    - Prayers and comforting Words (Box 26, Folder 327)
  - Writings
    - "Doctrine of The Will", 1890 June (Box 27, Folder 328)
    - "History of the Bible" (Box 27, Folder 329)
    - "Roman Catholic and Protestant Bible Compared" (by Beard), 1905 (Box 27, Folder 330)
  - Personal Items and Memorabilia
    - American Missionary Association (Box 27, Folder 331)
    - " A Picturesque Review, the Record of Half-Century", by L.H. Cobb (Box 27, Folder 332)
    - Cottage Guest Book (Box 27, Folder 333)
    - New Paper Articles on G. Beard (Box 27, Folder 334)
    - Order of Worship and Weekly Calender (Box 27, Folder 335)
    - Photographs (Box 27, Folder 336)
    - Writings by other authors (Box 28, Folder 337)
    - Yale Diplomas and Booklet of the Class of 1890 (Box 28, Folder 338)
    - Yale College; Yale Mission China, 1887/1917 (Box 28, Folder 339)